Guide to the Center for International Policy Records, 1960-2016 and undated; 1960-ongoing RL.00205
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Selig Harrison Papers, 1960-2011 and undated
  - Professional Subseries, 1991-2010 and undated
    - Knollwood Military Retirement Residence speech (Afghanistan, Pakistan and Balochistan), undated (Box 89)
    - Korea speech, undated (Box 89)
    - Korean Peninsula Peace Forum speech, 2006 Nov. 30 (Box 89)
    - Los Angelas Times regarding Pakistan, 2000-2006 (Box 89)
    - Le Monde Diplomatique - Alain Gresh regarding Iran, Pakistan, North Korea, etc., 2000-2010 and undated (Box 89)
    - Media - miscellaneous, undated (Box 89)
      Includes Foreign Service Journal, Al Jazeera, Charlie Rose, FOX, Time, C-Span, Democracy Now, etc.
    - Miscellaneous speeches, undated (Box 89)
    - The Nation regarding North Korea, 2004 (Box 89)
    - National Public Radio (NPR)and Free Speech Radio regarding Pakistan and Korea, 1994-2010 (Box 89)
    - News Hour regarding Pakistan, Kashmir, etc., 1999-2007 (Box 89)
    - Newsweek regarding North Korea, Bangladesh, India-Pakistan and Afghanistan debate, 2004-2009 (Box 89)
    - New York Times regarding North Korea, Japan, and India-United States nuclear, 1995-2010 and undated (Box 89)
    - New York Times Syndicate regarding Pakistan-Iran, 2003-2008 and undated (Box 89)
    - Northeast Asia speeches, 2001-2007 and undated (Box 90)
    - North Korean nuclear weapons program short speech, undated (Box 90)
    - "North Korean Perceptions of the United States: 'Hawks,' 'Doves' and the Normalization of Relations," 2005 Oct. 21-22 (Box 90)
    - "Nuclear Turning Point: Does the Quest for U.S. Nuclear Dominance Undermine Non-Proliferation?" remarks, 2006 May 8 (Box 90)
    - Other miscellaneous, 1998-2005 and undated (Box 90)
    - Pakistan, Afghanistan and India speeches, undated (Box 90)
    - Politico, 2004-2010 and undated (Box 90)
    - Possible pieces, including Kangan, Russia and Georgia, 2008 and undated (Box 90)
    - Press conference regarding Pakistan, 2005-2009 (Box 90)
    - Princeton speech, undated (Box 90)
    - Professional - miscellaneous, 2001-2003 (Box 90)
    - "Regional Energy Cooperation and the North Korean Nuclear Crisis," 2004 June 22-25 (Box 90)
    - "Report on North Korea," Johns Hopkins University, 2006 Sep. 28 (Box 90)
    - R.K. Narayanan tribute, undated (Box 90)
    - San Francisco speech regarding Democratic People's Republic of Korea nuclear, 2008 (Box 90)
    - San Francisco speech secondary regarding North Korea and United States nuclear policy, 2002-2003 (Box 90)
    - Speeches - Korea, undated (Box 90)
    - Speeches - North Korea-China, undated (Box 90)
    - Speeches prime, undated (Box 90)
    - Speech - Seoul, June 23 (Box 90)
    - "Taiwan and the World in the 21st Century," 1991 Aug. 22-23 (Box 90)
    - To the Point regarding Pakistan and Korea, 2006-2009 (Box 91)
    - United States-India Agreement speech, undated (Box 91)
    - United States Institute of Peace fellowship application - China, Japan, Korean Peninsula, cooperative development of seabed resources, 1998-1999 (Box 91)
    - USA Today regarding North Korea and Pakistan, 2002-2010 (Box 91)
    - Wall Street Journal regarding North Korea and Bangladesh, 2005-2009 (Box 91)
    - Washington Post/Outlook regarding Iran, Pakistan, Balochistan, North Korea, India, etc., 2000-2009 (Box 91)
    - Washington Times, 2001-2002 and undated (Box 91)
    - World Policy Journal, 2002 (Box 91)
- Wayne S. Smith Papers, 1980-2014
  This series contains files collected and created by Wayne S. Smith as part of his work with Center for International Policy. The materials include subject and research files on Cuba and U.S. trade and social policy, as well as writings by Smith opposing the U.S. Cuba embargo and travel restrictions, and travel files from Smith's work escorting students and lawmakers to Cuba on diplomatic and cultural missions.
  - Events and conference files, 1998-2009
    - Events and conference files, 1988-1999 (Box 95)
      Loosely arranged by year. Includes Smith's files and correspondence on events and conferences such as: The U.S. and Soviet Union in Latin America (1991); Cuba Transition workshop (1995); the Helms-Burton Act conference (1997); and the Consequences of Unilateralism (1998). Also includes his materials from various trips to Cuba.
    - Events and conference files, 1999-2002 (Box 96)
      Loosely arranged by year. Includes Smtih's events and conferences such as: Afro-Cuban conference (1999); CIP Board trip to Cuba (1999); Cross Cultural Journeys trips (1999, 2000); the U.S. and Cuban Trademarks conference (2001); trips to Cuba; and various lectures and trips visiting American universities.
    - Events and conference files, 2002-2005 (Box 97)
      Loosely arranged by year. Includes Smith's correspondence and files regarding events and conferences, such as: Cuban Missile Crisis 40th anniversary conference (2002); Cross Cultural Journeys trips (2003); Conference on Bush's New Cuban Policy (2004); National Summit on Cuba (2004, 2005); Guantanamo conference (2005); and others. Also includes materials from Smith's various trips to Cuba.
    - Events and conferences files, 2005-2009 and undated (Box 98)
  - Legal Cases, 1993-2008
    - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade - International Legal Materials, 1993-1994 (Box 98)
    - Helms-Burton Program, 1996 (Box 98)
    - Cuban American National Foundation vs. Wayne Smith: trial transcripts, 1996; 17 folders (Box 98)
      Trial transcripts of CANF's libel case against Wayne Smith; foldered as volumes 1-8.
    - Cuban American National Foundation vs. Wayne Smith: deposition of Carl Gershman, 1996 (Box 98)
    - Cuban American National Foundation vs. Wayne Smith: deposition of Robert Coonrod, 1995 (Box 98)
    - Cuban American National Foundation vs. Wayne Smith: deposition of Richard Carlson, 1995 (Box 98)
    - Cuban American National Foundation court case: miscellaneous materials, 1996-2000; 3 folders (Box 98)
    - United States vs. Gerardo Hernandez: Smith's subpoena and logistics, 2001 (Box 98)
    - Empresa Cubana del Tabaco vs. Culbro Corp. and General Cigar Co. Inc.: transcript of Smith's testimony, 2003 (Box 98)
    - Smith's testimony before the U.S. Senate Committee on Finance, 2003 (Box 98)
    - Smith's testimony to the U.S. House of Representatives' Committee on Government Reform: "The Capture and Treatment of Political Prisoners: One Year After Castro's Crackdown in Cuba", 2004 April (Box 98)
    - Ruben Campa, et al vs. United States of America, 2005; 6 folders (Box 98)
      Amicus brief, petition for writ of certiorari
    - Barcardi-Martini vs. Havana Club trademark/campaign contribution case, 2008 (Box 98)
  - Subject Files (General), 1980s-2000s
    - ABC/Disney consulting agreement, 2004-2006; 2 folders (Box 99)
    - Allyn, Bruce, 1989 (Box 99)
    - American Chamber of Commerce address, 1998 (Box 99)
    - Aragon, Ernesto, 2000 (Box 99)
    - Carriles, Luis Posada, 2005 (Box 99)
    - Casaus, Victor, 1998-1999 (Box 99)
    - Centro de Estudio Sobre Estados Unidos, 2000 (Box 99)
    - Christopher Reynolds Foundation proposals, files, 2002-2012 (Box 99)
    - Clinton, Bill: President's statement, 1999 Jan. 5 (Box 99)
    - Colomer, Joseph, 1996 (Box 99)
    - The Crawford Group, 2000 (Box 99)
    - Duffy, Gloria, 1983 (Box 99)
    - Enron, 2002 (Box 99)
    - Equador/drugs, 2000s (Box 99)
    - Feinsilver, Julia, 1993 (Box 99)
    - Ford Foundation grant files, 1997-2013 (Box 99)
    - Franco, Raimundo Garcia / Christian Center for Reflection and Dialogue, 1996-1998 (Box 99)
    - GALA theater, 2000 (Box 99)
    - Garthoff, Raymond, 1983 (Box 99)
    - Giuliano, Maurizio, 1997 (Box 99)
    - Gleijeses, Piero, 1991-1996 (Box 99)
    - Gonzalez, Elian, 1999-2000 (Box 99)
    - Grant applications, 2001 (Box 99)
    - Guantanamo interrogations, 2005 (Box 99)
    - Helms-Burton Act, 1996 (Box 99)
    - Kellogg proposal re: Cuba/healthcare, 2001 (Box 99)
    - Johns Hopkins Cuban Exchange program, 2000 (Box 99)
    - Leo Grande, William M., 1982 (Box 99)
    - Legislation on agricultural and medical exports, 1999 (Box 99)
    - Menoyo, Eloy Gutierrez, 2005 (Box 99)
    - Muse and Assoc. memo re: Cuba Policy in 110th Congress, 2007 (Box 99)
    - Nicaragua logging project, 2002-2006 (Box 100)
    - OAS, 1998 and undated (Box 100)
    - Ortiz, Fernando, 1996-1998 (Box 100)
    - Ponce, Carlos, re: Venezuelan legislation, 2006 (Box 100)
    - Radio Marti and TV Marti, 1994, 2002 (Box 100)
    - Reich, Otto, 2001 (Box 100)
    - Section 211, 2001-2002 (Box 100)
    - Siegleman, Leslie B., 2004 (Box 100)
    - Sloate, Joan, 2002-2003 (Box 100)
    - Spengler, Eusebio, 2001 (Box 100)
    - Tinker Foundation grant proposal, 2008 (Box 100)
    - USA-Cuba / InfoMed, 2003 (Box 100)
    - U.S. Institute of Peace, 1987-1991 (Box 100)
    - U.S. Office of Foreign Assets Control (specially designated nationals and blocked persons), 1995 (Box 100)
    - U.S. Sugar subsidies, 2003-2004 (Box 100)
    - Valdes, Nelson, 1980 (Box 100)
    - Veterans of Foreign Wars: Sister Cities, 2003 (Box 100)
  - Cuba Files, 1980s-2000s
    - AIDS, 1998 (Box 100)
    - The Bay of Pigs: New Evidence, 1983 (Box 100)
    - Cuban-American Defense League, 1996 and undated (Box 100)
    - Chronology of the Cuban Missle Crisis, 1988 (Box 100)
    - Congressional letters re: Cuba, 1996 (Box 100)
    - Consultation Day, 1998, 2000 (Box 100)
    - Cuban Liberty Act, 1996 (Box 100)
    - Drug policy, 1999 (Box 100)
    - Embassies in Cuba, 1995 (Box 100)
    - Guantanamo, 1978-1991 (Box 100)
    - Guidebooks / briefing book files, 1990s (Box 100)
    - CubaINFO issues, 1989-1994, 1999 (Box 101)
    - CubaINFO articles, 1994 (Box 101)
    - CubaINFO correspondence, 1996-2000 (Box 101)
    - CubaNews Business Guide to Cuba, 2000 (Box 101)
    - Inter-American Dialogue publications, 1995-1997 (Box 101)
    - Cuba and international terrorism, 2002, 2004 (Box 101)
    - Internet access, 2009 (Box 101)
    - Island Travel and Tours, Ltd., 2000s (Box 101)
    - Juragua Nuclear Power Plant, 1997 (Box 101)
    - Cuban migration, 2000-2002 (Box 101)
    - Moran (Congressman), 2005 (Box 101)
    - Printed literature re: Cuba, 1990s-2000s (Box 101)
    - Clippings and periodicals re: Cuba, 1980s-2000s (Box 101)
    - Proposals for branch offices in Havana, 1990s, 2005 (Box 101)
    - Rangel amendment / embargo, 2007 (Box 101)
    - Testimony of Geoff Thale, 2009 (Box 101)
    - Cuba / Soviet project, 1991-1993 (Box 101)
    - Travel legislation re: Cuba, 2000 (Box 101)
    - Travel ban and victims, 2002-2005 (Box 101)
    - Travel controls, 2002-2003 (Box 101)
    - Travel regulations, license, 2003-2011 (Box 101)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990s-2000s (Box 101)
  - Writings and correspondence, 1972-2013
    - Published writings, 1972-2013 (Box 94)
      Smith's assorted articles, editorials, reports, and book reviews spanning the 1970s through the 2000s. Topics include U.S. policy in Cuba, Fidel Castro, Latin America/Soviet relations, and others.
    - Interviews with Smith, 1992-2002 (Box 94)
    - Correspondence, assorted, 1990s-2000s (Box 94)
- Program, Subject, and Geographic Files, 1980s-2010s
  This series contains an array of documentation created by and collected by CIP program staff in support of various initiatives including promotion of democracy in Latin America, anti-corruption programs, anti-landmine programs and policies, and environmental protection policies. Programs represented include the CIP Central America Program (and its director, Elsa Chang), the Democracy without Borders project in Honduras; country programs in Nicaragua, Guatemala, and Colombia; and many files from various organizations working with CIP in political or fundraising partnerships. Also includes drafts of the CIP report "Commander in Chief", discussing the role of the American president in international treaties over landmines and chemical weapsons. Materials are loosely arranged by topic and are described at the box level.
  - Colombia, 2000s (Box 107, Box 94)
    CIP research files and collected information for Colombia briefing book; some correspondence and draft proposals for a meeting between US and FARC officials in the 2000s; Victims of the Armed Conflict project files (Medellin); CIP Colombia policy drafts and statements.
  - El Salvador, 1980s-2008 (Box 102, Box 103)
    CIP agency files regarding conditions and politics in El Salvador, collected and created by CIP staff. Includes materials from El Marcha, 2007-2008; CIP's Blue Democracy project (Democracia Azul), 2007-2008; and files from Robert White regarding El Salvador and his ambassadorship there, 2002-2007. Some of the Robert White material relates to a book draft, proposed and researched about White's time in El Salvador. Also includes a substantial amount of photocopied and gathered reports, declassified telegrams and other archival documents, and press releases regarding 1980s El Salvadorian death squads; includes materials collected about the murders of four U.S. churchwomen and subsequent investigations and trials.
  - Fundacion Democracia sin Fronteras (FDsF) / Democracy without Borders: Administration and reports, 2005-2008 (Box 104, Box 112)
    Includes administrative, funding, and logistical files from various meetings held by FDsF, as well as a briefing book and revised constitution from the founding of the NGO by CIP. Contains some scattered annual reports and media coverage. Programs mentioned include the FDsF inauguration, held in Honduras in 2006, as well as the Mateo city program and the Transparency and Access to Information program.
  - Honduras, 2000-2007 (Box 105, Box 111)
    Files related to CIP activities in Honduras, particularly regarding violence stemming from illegal logging and deforestation. Includes some FDsF materials, as well as research and documentation of negotiations and confrontations between loggers and the military in Olancho versus the MAO (Olancho's Environmental Movement) and other civilians. Includes materials researching the death of anti-logging activist Carlos Reyes. CIP staff represented include Adam Isaacson, Elsa Chang, and Robert White, among others. There is also extensive material from the CIP-sponsored Marcha Nacional por la Vida, held in June 2004 to protest deforestation in Honduras, as well as material documenting the at-times contentious relationship between CIP and EIA (Environmental Investigation Agency). Some other topics represented by subject files include CAFTA (Central America Free Trade Agreement), mining, corruption, the 2005 election, and human rights in Honduras.
  - Central America Program materials, 2000s (Box 106, Box 112)
    Budget proposals, program workplans, and statutes from the founding of the FDsF, as well as other country programs within the CIP's Central America Program.
  - Guatemala, 1990s-2000s (Box 107)
    Subject files, correspondence, published NGO handouts, and clippings collected by CIP regarding Guatemalan government corruption, mining, and violence/human rights violations. Largely dating from the 2000s but includes copies of earlier materia.
  - Nicaragua, 1980s-2000s (Box 107, Box 108)
    Largely files relating to CIP and FDsF's exposure and investigation into illegal logging in Nicaragua, including reports, conferences, a contract with Environmental Impact Agency (EIA), plans for press releases and a documentary, and event files. Includes Bob Levinson's research into the Nicaraguan forest mafia. Also includes some research materials regarding Nicaragua political conditions in the 1980s.
  - Illegal logging, 2000s (Box 108, Box 111)
    Press coverage and clippings regarding illegal logging in Central America.
  - Central America news coverage, publications, 1990s-2000s (Box 108)
    Assorted articles and press coverage of Central American politics, events, and other CIP-related subjects, collected by CIP staff.
  - Africa Program materials, 1999-2000s (Box 109)
    Seminar packets for assorted institutes, clippings and research articles, and other materials collected and created by CIP Africa Program staff. Minimal correspondence or programmatic files; appears to be largely research and reference material. Countries include Senegal, Angola, and Nigeria; files also contain material regarding American foreign relations and security in Africa.
  - Military training and spending, 2001-2006 (Box 109)
    Assorted materials researching and documenting United States and other European country military spending in African, Central American, and Asian countries. Includes materials related to terrorism, arms control, training expenditures and programs, and other topics of interest to CIP such as oil and political elections.
  - Landmines and demilitarization, 1993-2000s (Box 110)
    Research files and program material for various initiatives in the 1990s and early 2000s seeking to ban and disarm landmines and other explosives used globally during military occupation and war. Includes materials from the Ottawa Treaty to ban mines; publications and press releases from demilitarization and anti-mine organizations and CIP programs like Demilitarization for Democracy and the International Campaign to Ban Landmines; Congressional and international legislative efforts; press articles, pamphlets, and coverage of the devestation caused by landmines; and materials documenting the U.S. refusal to join treaties banning landmines. One file includes an autographed letter from President Bill Clinton explaining his administration's refusal to endorse a full ban on landmines.
  - "Commander-In-Chief: The Role of Presidential Leadership in Efforts to Ban the Use of Chemical Weapons and Landmines," CIP report: drafts and sources, 1998-1999 (Box 111)
  - Deforestation and environmental agency partners, 2000s (Box 112)
    Assorted files for different agencies collected by CIP staff, including Associacion para una Sociedad Justa (ASJ), IRELA, Partners for Democractic Change, Earthworks, Transparency International, CEDHA, and others.
- Audiovisual Materials, 1990s-2007; 1
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services in advance to request the production of use copies.
  - Cuba Conference, 2004 Oct. 21 (Box 114, Video-cassette RL00205-VHS-001)
    "tape 1 of 2"
  - Free to Fly: The U.S. Cuba Link, undated (Box 114, Video-cassette RL00205-VHS-002)
  - CIP: Afro-Cubans in Cuban Society Final Panel: The Future, 1999 Sept. 15-17 (Box 114, Video-cassette RL00205-VHS-003)
  - The World Stopped Watching, 2003 (Box 114, Video-cassette RL00205-VHS-004)
    Produced and directed by Peter Raymont. Documentary film about the return of journalists to Nicaragua 15 years after Contra/Sandinista period.
  - In favor of the human rights of indigenous peoples / fighting for the legal self-defense groups in favor of human rights: Ministerio de Defensa Nacional Republica de Colombia, undated (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-DVD-001)
  - Subtle Voices: Cries from Colombia, undated (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-DVD-002)
    Documentary film by Andrew "Buzz" Patterson
  - La Vigencia de los Derechos Humanos en la Seguridad y Defensa, 2007 Mar 20-22 (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-DVD-003)
    "Measuring Progress and Respect for Human Rights: Human Rights Initiative", Miami conference
  - Bolivarian Rule of Lawlessness: The Eligio Cedeno Case, undated (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-DVD-004)
    The Erosion of Judicial Autonomy under Hugo Chavez, by Robert Amsterdam, Gonzalo Himiob Santome, and Antonio Rosich
  - Casa de Paz: Casa de la Gente, undated (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-DVD-005)
  - Visita del Comandante: Antonio Garcia a Dasa de Paz, 2006 Apr. 17-21 (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-DVD-006)
  - Congreso Nacional de Honduras: Ley Forestal, 2006 Oct. 12 (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-DVD-007)
    Fundacion Democracia sin Fronteras
  - Kwame Ture/Stokely Carmichael, 1990s-2000s (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-DVD-008)
  - Tocar y Luchar, 2006 (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-DVD-009)
    Documentary about Venezuelan Youth Orchestra System (To Play and to Fight) by Alberto Arvelo
  - Cunas de Radio Cardenal O.A.R, 2006 Aug.-Sept. (Box 114, Video-disc RL00205-CDR-001)
  - Selig Harrison Audiovisual Subseries, 2002-2007 and undated
    Contains discs, diskettes and audio cassettes removed from the Geographic, Nucelar and Energy, and Professional subseries. Materials are organized alphabetically by name.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    [[Access to electronic records is restricted. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this subseries.]
    - Afghanistan disk, open "index.html" first, undated, 1 diskette (Box 92)
      This is a small website on disk. Will open in any browser.
    - Article 1 in plain, 2002 Oct., 1 diskette (Box 92)
    - Article 1 in bold, 2002 Oct., 2 diskettes (Box 92)
    - Article 4 in plain, 2002 Oct., 1 diskette (Box 92)
    - Article, 2002 Oct., 2 diskettes (Box 92)
    - Balochistan and North Korea, 2004 May 8, 3 tapes (Box 92)
    - Balochistan and North Korea, Brojerdi, undated, 1 tape (Box 92)
    - Balochistan and North Korea, Center for International Policy meeting, Stein Room, 2-4:30pm, 2003 Feb. 25, 1 tape (Box 92)
    - Balochistan and North Korea, Mottaki's speech, undated, 1 tape (Box 92)
    - Balochistan and North Korea task force meeting, 2003 Jan. 9, 4 tapes (Box 92)
    - Balochistan and North Korea - Shariatma dari speech, undated, 1 tape (Box 92)
    - Beyond Top Secret: Iran, The History Channel, Friday Nov. 2, 8pm; Saturday Nov. 3, 12pm; Monday Nov. 5, 11pm; Tuesday Nov. 6, 3am, 1 disc (Box 92)
    - Current History (Asia oil), 2002 Sep., 1 diskette (Box 92)
    - Event in Saul room, tape 4, 2004, 1 tape (Box 92)
    - Hankyoreh past, undated, 1 diskette (Box 92)
    - India-Pakistan trade, undated, 1 disc (Box 92)
    - Korea research prime - Joschka Fisher interviews - Spiegel, Sueddeutsche (translations), Word Perfect 6, undated, 1 diskette (Box 92)
    - Masoud Khodabndeh, Press TV News Analysis, undated, 1 disc (Box 92)
    - MKO cult of the chameleon, Aljazeera Channel, 2007 Oct. 17, 1 disc (Box 92)
    - North Korea agriculture - "NKTRADE.WK3," Dyck, United States Department of Agriculture, undated, 1 diskette (Box 92)